# 这个醋 绝了
This vinegar. Perfect
# 这面条真是好吃
The noodles are so delicious.
# 大爷就是大爷
Da Ye is Da Ye. (A good sword remains always sharp.)
# 最家常的茄子汆儿面
The homeliest eggplant noodle.
# 茄子丁切的稍微大点
dice eggplant into larger pieces
# 一会一煸一炒 没了
otherwise they will be shirked too small after stir-frying.
# 切成什么丁呢 色子丁
chop into what of pieces? Like dice.
# 这个季节正是吃茄子的时候
This is eggplant season.
# 连个籽儿儿都没有
The eggplant even doesn’t have any seeds.
# 买茄子买什么样的茄子 买轻的茄子
What kind of eggplants should we buy? Lighter ones.
# 那茄子一说沉了 籽儿多了 老了
If eggplant is heavier, which means it contains more seeds. Too ripe.( past the best edible time)
# 刚强给我倒点油
Gang Qiang, add some oil for me.
# 还得倒 油少了不好吃 茄子吸油
Add more, less oil makes untasted eggplant. Eggplant absorbs oil.
# 来俩大料瓣 煸茄子
Add two star anises. Stir-fry the eggplant.
# 有肉味 增加肉的香味
Meat Aroma. It can add some meat aroma (into the dish)
# 你给攉拢着啊 我来切肉
Stirring it for me. Let me cut the meat.
# 爱吃肉的多搁点 不爱吃肉的少搁
Meat lovers can add more meat, otherwise, cut less.
# 但是我们一定要搁点什么 肥瘦的五花肉
But, what we should add? Pork belly.
# 茄子不能加水 就干煸
Shouldn't add water in the eggplant. Just Stir-frying alone.
# 烧茄子我可以不油炸 那怎么办
I can cook eggplant without deep-frying. What should we do?
# 咱家里要有那平铛
We need to have flat frying pan at home.
# 把茄子切成厚片 煎 干煎
Cut the eggplant into thick slice. Pan-fir, dry-sautéed.
# 煎到一定程度的时候再搁油
To a certain degree, add some oil into the pan-fired eggplant.
# 大爷今儿这肉可不少 我来点小料
Da Ye prepared lots of meat. Let me prepare some spices.
# 你看这茄子下去了吧 好了
Check out the shirked eggplants. Okay.
# 这俩大茄子就煸出这么点儿来
Two large eggplants just left these (little) amount.
# 这茄子味浓 香吧
The aroma of the eggplant is very rich. Smells good.
# 今天我这个茄子汆儿面
Today, my eggplant noodle
# 还有一个小秘方 我们拍点蒜
have another secret tip. Smash some garlics with knife.
# 因为吃茄子蒜不能少
Because we can't have eggplants without garlic.
# 砸点蒜泥也行 剁点蒜末也行
Or granulate some garlic minces. Or you can just chop some garlic.
# 这个蒜因为要生吃
We need to eat raw (uncooked) garlic,
# 所以咱们换了一个菜板
so let’s change to another chopping board.
# 生熟分开 米醋有没有
Separate uncooked and cooked ingredients (with different chopping board). Do we have rice vinegar?
# 这叫醋蒜 这要早点给它泡上 让它氧化
It is called as garlic vinegar. Mix and rest it in the morning to oxidize.
# 氧化了让这大蒜的味道
Oxidizing the smell and taste of the garlic
# 更加浓郁的往出给它释放出来
is to realise the rich aroma of the smell in the garlic.
# 好了 来点小油儿
Okay. Add little oil.
# 肉丁下锅 一定要把肉的水分
Put diced meat in the pan. Moisture in the diced meat
# 给它煸出去 煸透 然后出油
needs to be stir-fired until fully evaporated, fully stir-fried and expressing oil.
# 这油在锅里边变成一种明亮的油
The oil becomes brighter in the pan.
# 有的有油也有汤 发浑
Some oil might be mixed with meat juice, (the oil) is turbid.
# 那个不行 出来以后容易腥
That is not okay as the meat will have unpleasant taste and smell.
# 你看这肉丁为什么要切大一点
The reason why we diced meat into larger piece
# 一煸它就小了 来俩大料瓣 煸出油来
is because meat will shrink during stir-frying process. Add two star anises, stir-frying until express oil.
# 把小料放进去 小料得足（葱花 姜末）
Add more condiments in. Enough condiments (diced spring onion and ginger mince)
# 要想香料得足
We need enough condiments and spices.
# 黄酒 酱油
Huangjiu rice wine, soy sauce
# 我就事儿把这瓶子给清了
I used up the rest in this bottle.
# 没酱油不好吃
Without soy sauce, it doesn't taste good.
# 来点老抽
Add some dark soy sauce.
# 这差不多了 颜色上来了吧
It almost ready. The colour turns to be good.
# 来点盐
Add some salt.
# 胡椒粉
Pepper powder.
# 来点糖
some sugar.
# 现在可以煮面了
Now we can blanch noodles.
# 茄子搁么 茄子等会 我再咕嘟咕嘟肉
Should I put eggplants in? Eggplants can wait. I need to cook the meat longer.
# 咕嘟着让它入味
Boiling will help the meat to absorb deeper and more delicious flavour.
# 这个菜里边不要着急老早放盐
Don't add salt too early.
# 一放盐一杀水 出汤了
Salt will let the dish bring out water and juice.
# 茄子现在已经是基本上快熟了
Eggplants are basically cooked.
# 我们把这里边的大料瓣给挑出来
We take out star anises in the dish.
# 全程大火 面条下锅去煮
Cooking with high heat during the whole process. Add the noodles in.
# 咱们把茄子倒里头
Let’s put eggplants in as well.
# 熬这茄子让它入味
Boiling out the eggplants to let them absorb flavours.
# 颜色红亮
Bright red colour.
# 下面条 切面
Add noodles, cut noodles.
# 先尝一个 入进去了
Taste one. Add in.
# 关火了 慢慢咕嘟着 余热
Turn off the fire. Cooking it slowly with residual heat.
# 一点水没加 入味了
We didn’t add any water. Flavours in.
# 有的比如爱吃辣的它可以切两刀小米辣
If you love spicy food, you can add some “Xiaomila” chilli pepper (red hot pepper).
# 搁这里头了
add it in.
# 这个面就不用去过水 锅挑 出锅喽
No need to blanch in cold water, get it out directly from pot. ready to serve.
# 今天的量都够足的
Food today all come in big portion.
# 喜兴 现在就把茄子汆给它上上
Looks good. Pour the eggplants and meat mixture on top of it.
# 在疫情当中 我在家给做了一回
At this pandemic period, I cooked this dish at home.
# 全家人大受欢迎
My family love it a lot.
# 拿一勺子 二伯
Grab a spoon. Er Bai.
# 吃茄子一定要有醋蒜
For eggplant, you must accompany with some garlic vinegar.
# 二伯您是来一碗还是来一口
Er Bai, do you want a bowl or just a bite?
# 来一口 我吃了一天面了
Just a bite. I had noodle dishes all day.
# 这蒜加的好
The garlic is the highlight.
# 大料提的肉香味 全提出来
Star anises brings out the aroma of meat. All of it.
# 这经典之笔就在于什么
The finishing touch is
# 这个蒜和醋 这个醋绝了
this garlic and vinegar. This is terrific!
# 再来一口
Give me another bite.
# 我跟你说小魏
Let me tell you something, Xiao Wei.
# 大爷就是大爷
Da Ye is Da Ye (A good sword remains always sharp.)
Watermelon with skin 2330g (RMB 9.3 per unit)
Agar 8.5g (RMB 2.7 per bag)
Shaban Sugar (Traditional Sugar from Beijing) 60g (RMB 25 to 30 per piece)
Water 400g
(May not be suitable for pregnant women)
Step 1 – Soak 8.5g agar in spring water for half hour. Add water to fully cover agar-agar. (Expansion ratio 1:15.8)
Step 2 – Squeeze 1300g watermelon juicy from 2330g watermelon.
Step 3 – Filter foam and prepare Shaban sugar.
Step 4- Smash 60g sugar and add 200g warm water. The water temperature should be between 40 to 60 degrees. When the sugar dissolves naturally in the water, put in fridge.
Step 5 – After agar is fully soaked and swelling. Add 200g spring water and heat with low flame.
Step 6 – Add agar into watermelon juice from strainer.
Step 7 – Mix and stir agar-agar and juice together gently. Divide the mixture into 12 small bowls and rest in fridge for 2 hours.
Step 8 – Add mint leaf on top of it.